THIS STORY IS A FICION, AND ALL NAMES OF FIGURES ND ORGANIZATIONS ARE FICTITIOUS.
（本作所有人物、组织名均为虚构）
MOREOVER, THE STORY HAS NO RELATION TO REAL-LIFE INCIDENTS AND EVENTS.
（与任何特定事件或现象无关）
A letter from Concubine Gyokuyou?
玉叶妃送来的信？
Yes. I was asked to deliver this directly to her.
是 说是要直接交给本人
Lady Ah-Duo is currently at a tea party.
阿多娘娘正在参加茶会呢
I need to talk to you about something, Ms. Fengming.
风明大人 我有些话想和您说
All right.
我知道了
She's packed her things.
家当都已经收拾好了
So that means…
也就是说 果然…
Here you are.
请慢用
So, what brings you here today?
那么 你今天过来到底所为何事呢？
We're all set with the New Year's cleaning.
大扫除已经处理得差不多了
When are you moving?
您何时要搬走？
You're perceptive.
你的直觉真敏锐
The New Year's cleaning was just a front for the real purpose.
大扫除只是表面上的理由
Once the New Year arrives,
在祝贺新年到来的同时
Concubine Ah-Duo must leave this pavilion
为了迎娶新的上级妃
to make space for the new high-ranking concubine.
阿多妃不得不离开这座宫殿
Lady Ah-Duo can't have children anymore.
阿多妃再也无法生子了吧
What happened during the birth?
在生产时发生了什么事？
I don't think that's relevant to you.
这件事应该跟你没关系吧？
It's not totally irrelevant.
并不是毫无关系
It was my father who attended the birth.
在现场接生的人 是我的养父
The unfortunate thing was that the birth by Lady Ah-Duo, the concubine for
不幸的是 还是东宫妃子的阿多妃在生产时
the Eastern Palace, coincided with the former Empress's delivery date.
与当时皇后产子的时间碰在一起
The physician hasn't returned yet?
医官还没回来吗？
He's still with the Empress.
他仍然在皇后那儿
Lady Ah-Duo! Lady Ah-Duo, it'll be all right!
阿多娘娘…一切会没事的
Fengming is by your side.
风明在这儿陪着您
Compared to the Empress,
与皇后一同摆上天平衡量的结果
Lady Ah-Duo's birth was less of a priority.
阿多妃的临盆被排在了后头
Lady Ah-Duo!
阿多娘娘
That must be when
就是在那个时候
Lady Ah-Duo lost her uterus.
阿多妃失去了子宫
After that, the child born to Lady Ah-Duo
之后 阿多妃生下的孩子
lost his life at a young age.
也在幼年时夭折了
Perhaps you feel responsible for what happened, Ms. Fengming.
风明大人 您是不是认为自己该负起责任呢？
You must have been the one looking after the baby
当时代替产后身体欠安的阿多妃
while Concubine Ah-Duo was unwell.
照顾孩子的 应该是您吧？
So you know everything, huh?
你还真是什么都知道呢
You, the daughter of the worthless doctor who couldn't save Lady Ah-Duo.
明明只是个 帮不了阿多娘娘的庸医之女
That's true.
确实如此
LUOMEN
（罗门 流放）
They say the baby's cause of death
有人怀疑孩子的死因
was the same as the poisonous face powder from before.
与先前的有毒白粉事件一样
But that's not true, is it?
但事实并非如此 对吧？
The "worthless doctor," as you put it,
您口中的“庸医”
must have forbidden the use of the face powder.
一定禁止过大家使用白粉
Someone as intelligent as you
聪慧如您的人
wouldn't let the baby die from such a thing.
不可能因为这样害死孩子
The true cause of death was…
真正的死因是…
This.
这个
There are many flowers with poison.
许多花朵是有毒的
Like aconite and azalea.
例如乌头和莲华踯躅
And its syrup contains poison as well.
它们就连花蜜也含有毒素
I know that.
我知道
But you didn't know.
但您有所不知
You didn't know that regular honey without any poison,
没有毒的寻常蜂蜜
medicine said to be good for nourishment,
一般被视为是营养丰富的良药
could be poisonous for babies.
但对婴儿来说可能是毒药
Thank you for your help, Fengming.
抱歉总是麻烦你 风明
Not at all. You should rest, Lady Ah-Duo,
不敢当 阿多娘娘应该好好休养身体
and focus on your recovery.
赶快恢复元气才是
Later, Concubine Ah-Duo's child passes away.
不久后 阿多妃的孩子就没了气息
The cause of death was unknown.
死因成谜
My father Luomen, a court physician at the time,
当时的医官 也就是我的养父罗门
was banished from the rear palace
由于生产时的处置不当 加上此事
due to his repeated mistakes, including
遭人以连续失职为由
his treatment during the birth.
逐出后宫
After that, by chance, you happened to learn
之后 您在偶然之间
the cause of Lady Ah-Duo's child's death.
知道了阿多妃孩子的真正死因
A certain person told you that honey is poisonous to babies.
某人告诉过您 蜂蜜对婴儿有毒的事情 对吧？
You wanted to prevent Concubine Ah-Duo from learning
您不想让阿多妃知道
that you caused the death of her only child.
您就是害死她唯一孩子的原因
That's why you tried to get rid of them.
所以您才想要除之后快
That person was…
那个“某人”就是…
Concubine Lishu.
里树妃
During the reign of the former Emperor,
先帝在位时
Lady Lishu was attached to the older Lady Ah-Duo.
里树妃与年长的媳妇阿多妃 关系非常亲近
Lady Ah-Duo also cared deeply for Lady Lishu.
阿多妃也很疼爱里树妃
A young girl who left home
和双亲分离的年幼女童
and a woman who will no longer have children.
与再也无法生儿育女的女子
Perhaps there was a type of codependency forming.
她们之间也许 产生了一种相互依存的关系
One day, you learn from Lady Lishu
然而某天 您从里树妃那儿得知
that she ate some honey as a baby and almost died.
她在婴儿时期 曾因吃了蜂蜜差点丧命的事
To prevent Lady Ah-Duo from hearing this,
为了避免阿多妃发现这件事
you started to turn Lady Lishu away from the Garnet Pavillion.
您开始禁止里树妃出入柘榴宫
Eventually, the former Emperor died,
最终 先帝驾崩
and Lady Lishu entered the temple, not knowing why she was turned away.
里树妃始终不明白被赶走的理由 就这样子出家了
You must've been relieved, Ms. Fengming.
风明大人 您一定感到如释重负吧
You thought you'd never see Lady Lishu again.
但您没想到 以为再也不会见面的里树妃
But she returned to the rear pavilion.
却再次出现在后宫
As another high-ranking concubine.
并同样作为上级妃
As someone who would replace Lady Ah-Duo's position.
站在可能威胁阿多妃的地位上
The pushy girl continued to visit Lady Ah-Duo
然而这恬不知耻的小女孩
again and again, as if in search of a mother figure.
却像是为了寻求母亲一般 持续地来拜访阿多妃
To protect the position of Lady Ah-Duo, who can't have children,
为了维护不孕的阿多妃的地位
and to hide the honey incident,
也为了隐藏蜂蜜意外的真相
you placed poison in Lady Lishu's soup.
您便在里树妃的汤里下毒
What is it that you want?
你想要什么？
I don't want anything.
我没有想要什么
I'll get you whatever you'd like.
想要什么都可以哦
You know more than anyone that threats like that are pointless.
那种话一点意义都没有 您自己应该也知道吧？
Have you ever known the most cherished thing
你知道你最珍爱的人
of the person you most hold dear?
最珍爱的是什么吗？
Ever since I met Lady Ah-Duo for the first time,
打从我见到阿多娘娘的那一刻起
I knew I wouldn't serve anyone else.
我就知道我再也不会侍奉其他主子了
Though she was a woman,
虽然她身为女子
she had a strong will, and could converse on equal terms with the Eastern Palace.
却有坚定的意志 能够和东宫以相同的观点对谈
I respected Lady Ah-Duo from the bottom of my heart.
我打从心底尊敬阿多娘娘
I was just a girl
比起只会听从父母之言
who blindly followed her parents to become a maid.
顺从他们意见而成为侍女的我
Meeting her changed my life.
她给我的震撼是多么的大
But I…
但是我却…
I used these hands to take away Lady Ah-Duo's most cherished thing…
我却夺走了阿多娘娘最珍爱的人
I did that to her!
我用这双手夺走了
The baby that Lady Ah-Duo cherished like a precious diamond!
阿多娘娘当成心肝宝贝的孩子啊！
With these hands…
都是这双手…
Do you know
那时…
what Lady Ah-Duo said to us then?
阿多娘娘对我们这样说过
Do not sadden yourselves over this.
大家不必为了这件事情难过
A child's life is never certain until the age of seven.
孩子在七岁之前 会发生什么事没有人知道
A small illness can quickly take their lives.
生了一点小病就很容易丧命
My son simply followed heaven's orders.
我的孩子只是天命如此罢了
Even though I knew Lady Ah-Duo
但阿多娘娘每晚都以泪洗面
cried herself to sleep every night!
我明明是知道的
How did she feel as she served her lady these past 16 years?
这十六年来 她究竟是抱着 何种心情在服侍阿多妃呢？
Without even having a husband,
甚至也不找个丈夫
she worked tirelessly for Concubine Ah-Duo…
只是一心为阿多妃鞠躬尽瘁
I would never understand.
我没办法体会
I don't have the heart to care for someone this deeply.
我没有这种如此珍爱他人的心情
If I tell the truth,
如果听了我的说法
Sir Jinshi will capture Ms. Fengming for sure.
壬氏大人一定会将风明捉拿归案吧
Regardless of the circumstances, she won't escape the death penalty.
无论如何 一定是逃不了酷刑的
She's intelligent. She must know all of this.
她很聪明 这些她一定都明白
I have an idea.
我有一个提案
The only thing I can do
我唯一能做的
is to reduce the two motives into one.
就是将这两个动机减为一个
The result will be the same.
结果不会改变
Please tell me if you will accept.
如果这样可以的话 还请接受这个提案吧
I'm so tired.
累死了
I don't have time for a bath. But I can get changed, at least.
没有办法洗澡 但至少换个衣服好了
I layered some oil paper just in case,
为了以防万一 迭了好几层油纸
but I'm glad I didn't need it.
没有用上真是太好了
Being stabbed is painful.
被砍的话应该很痛吧
So, Fengming turned herself in.
所以说 风明自首了
Do you know anything?
你知道些什么吗？
I have no idea what you're talking about.
大人是指什么事呢？
I heard you had Gaoshun gather some documents.
我听说你要高顺收集了一些册籍
Yes. I thought I could learn something,
对 我以为能够弄明白些什么
but it was pointless.
但结果只是白忙一场
Fengming's motive, as you guessed, was for Concubine Ah-Duo.
风明的动机就如你所说的那样 是为了阿多妃
She did it to protect her position amongst the Four Ladies.
为了守住她身为四夫人的地位
I see.
这样啊
But it's already been decided that Lady Ah-Duo will step down.
但让阿多妃从上级妃退下的事情 已经决定了
She'll live in a villa in the south after leaving the rear palace.
她在离开后宫之后 将会住到南方的离宫
Was that decided because of this incident?
是因为这次事件的关系吗？
No. It had been decided for a while.
不是 原本早已决定好了
-It was the Emperor's decision. -I see.
-是皇帝下的决定 -是哦
This flower…
这些花…
I saw Hongniang decorate those earlier.
刚刚红娘来装饰的
Yes. They're blooming out of season.
嗯 不是当季却盛开着呢
-It's sweet. -It's poison.
-好甜 -有毒就是了
You won't die. Don't worry.
不会死人的 放心吧
The proposal I made to Fengming…
那时向风明提出的提案是…
The poisoning of Lady Lishu, and the cause of death of the baby.
对里树妃下毒以及孩子的死因
If I reduce the two motives into one,
如果我将两个动机减为一个
Lady Ah-Duo will never know the cause of her baby's death.
阿多妃便永远不会知道 孩子的真正死因
Though she cannot prevent her own death…
虽然自身难逃一死…
That was the most that I, a girl with no power at all,
这是没有任何权力的小姑娘
could do in that situation.
所能做到最大限度的事情了
I can't sleep…
睡不着啊
I'll take a walk.
去散散步好了
Fengming's execution was completed.
风明的处刑结束了
Tomorrow, Concubine Ah-Duo will leave the rear palace.
明天 阿多妃就会离开后宫
Oh. Looks like it's occupied.
哎呀 看来有人先我一步
You're the maid who came to help the other day.
你是前几天来帮忙的那个侍女
-I'll leave right away. -That's all right.
-我这就离开 -没关系
Won't you have a drink with me?
陪我喝一杯吧
Alcohol!
酒！
Thank you very much, ma'am!
谢谢您
I'm like a man, right?
我像个男人 对吧？
It looks like you're trying to act that way.
您的举止看似是如此
You're honest, aren't you?
真是老实啊
After my son left me, for many years,
自从孩子从我怀中离去之后
I wasn't a concubine, but the Emperor's friend.
我就不是妃子 而一直是皇帝的朋友
No. More like, I went back to being his friend.
不 应该说“变回”了朋友
I never imagined I'd become a concubine.
我从未想过我会成为妃子
I was just a concubine for decoration, because he pitied me.
原本只是出于情份 而当个装饰用的妃子
I wanted to hand over my position as soon as I could.
早就想将这个位置让给他人
Why did I obsess over this for so long?
为什么却又紧抓着不放呢？
No matter who was with her tonight,
这晚无论在她身边的是谁
she would've said the same thing.
她都会说出同样的话吧
It must've been cold inside the water.
水里一定很冷吧
She must've suffered a lot.
一定很难受吧
I think so.
应该是吧
Stupid, right?
真傻啊
Perhaps.
或许是吧
Everyone. They're so stupid.
大家都太傻了
I think I know now.
我想我现在明白了
That maid must have killed herself.
那个婢女果然是自杀的
Concubine Ah-Duo knew this.
阿多妃应该也知道这件事
Perhaps Fengming played a part in her suicide.
风明或许也参与了自杀事件
The maid who jumped into the cold water
为了不让阿多妃遭到怀疑
so that Concubine Ah-Duo wouldn't be suspected.
而沉入冰冷水中的婢女
Fengming, who stepped onto the gallows willingly
为了守住不想让人知道的秘密
to protect a secret she wanted to keep.
而自己走上绞刑台的风明
It doesn't matter what Lady Ah-Duo's wishes are.
跟阿多妃的意愿没有关系
She has women who risk their lives for her.
有些人就是会为了她拼上性命
I should climb down soon.
我也该下去了
What are you doing?!
你在做什么？
Who is it? You surprised me!
谁啊？突然吓了我一跳
Sorry about that.
真是抱歉啊
Sir Jinshi, why are you here?
壬氏大人 您为什么在这儿？
That's my line.
那是我要问的吧
I'm sorry. I'll get out of the way.
对不起 我现在就起来…
Will you let me go?
可以请您放开吗？
Let me go, please.
请放开
It's cold. I don't want to.
很冷 不要
You'll catch a cold without a coat.
您没穿外衣很容易感冒的
You should go back.
请快回屋里去吧
Are you drunk?
您喝酒了吗？
It's a part of my job. I have to.
是应酬 没办法
A part of his job, huh?
应酬啊
The head of the house invited me for a drink,
屋主邀我喝酒
made me drink as much as I could, then went off somewhere.
要我拚命喝 结果喝完后 主人不知道跑哪儿去了
When she finally returned,
那个人终于回来后
she said she felt much better, so I should go home.
却说心情畅快多了 便把我赶出来叫我回去
I didn't know there were people in this rear palace
我都不知道后宫竟然也有人
who could treat him that way.
能如此对待这位大人
But that's neither here nor there.
但这和那是两回事
I don't have the time to be around this clingy drunkard!
我一点都不想和这个黏人的醉汉作伴
Wait. Now that I think about it,
等等 仔细想想的话…
he caught me because I fell down.
刚刚是我掉了下来 他才会接住我
Maybe it's rude to ask him to let go of me
没有先感谢他 便要他放开我
without thanking him first.
也许的确是失礼了点
Sir Jinshi…
壬氏大人…
Just a little longer.
再一下就好
Warm me for a little bit more.
再给我一点温暖就好
Looks like they're not dealing with a hangover.
看来不用担心这两人会宿醉呢
In order to leave the rear palace,
阿多妃由于要离开后宫
Lady Ah-Duo will hand over her Pure Concubine crown.
因此要将代表淑妃身分的头冠交还
After a while, that crown will be given
那顶头冠在不久之后
to the new girl who will enter the court.
便会交给新入宫的妃子了吧
Oh, I see. I thought she looked like someone.
对哦 还觉得有点像谁呢
It was Sir Jinshi.
原来是像壬氏大人啊
They'd look better if they swapped clothes…
要是两人交换服装 应该会更适合…
"Swapped?"
“交换”？
After my son left me, for many years…
“自从孩子从我怀中离去之后”
After he "left" her? Not "died"?
是“离去”而不是“死去”吗？
That could be interpreted to mean that he's still alive.
这说法听起来 简直就像孩子还活着一样
Lady Ah-Duo's child and the child of the Empress, born at the time…
在同一时间出生 阿多妃的孩子与当时皇后的孩子…
What if those two babies were swapped?
如果那两个孩子被掉包的话呢？
Concubine Ah-Duo must've experienced in her bones that…
生产当时 阿多妃的亲身经历 应该让她明白到…
What are you doing? I'm not done with Lady Ah-Duo…
你要做什么？ 我还在帮阿多娘娘接生…
The Empress is the priority!
皇后更重要
No!
怎么能这样？
…She's merely the daughter of a wet nurse.
自己不过是奶娘的女儿
That rather than the child of the step-sibling concubine,
只是东宫的乳姐弟 比起在自己这样的妃子身边
the child born to the Empress at the time
当时皇后所生下的孩子
would have more protection.
肯定能受到更多呵护吧
Perhaps she couldn't judge right from wrong at the time.
也许她当时已经无法明辨是非了
But if her own son would be saved as a result…
但如果因此而让自己的孩子得救
That would have been Lady Ah-Duo's only wish.
那么阿多妃的愿望也就实现了吧
Suppose that it was found out that the babies were swapped.
假设日后孩子掉包的事迹败露
If this was after the baby had died,
如果是发生在那个孩子死去之后
it would make sense that old man received corporal punishment
由于没注意到孩子被掉包 老爹因此受到肉刑
for not noticing the swap.
也就能理解了
That would explain why the Emperor's brother is in an unstable position,
若是如此 现在所处地位微妙的皇弟
and why the gracious Lady Ah-Duo stayed in the rear palace
以及清洁高尚的阿多妃为何留在后宫
without making efforts to leave…
并无意离开的理由也说得通了
This is all pointless. It's just a crazy fantasy.
真是无聊透顶 全是些愚蠢的妄想
Please wait!
请留步！
Lady Lishu!
里树娘娘！
They haven't changed, it seems.
这边还是老样子呢
For an isolated concubine to have an attendant she could confide in…
孤独的妃子 有了一位可以信赖的侍女
What a relief that must be for them.
那是一件多么令人感到欣慰的事啊
Lady Lishu!
里树娘娘
In that moment, that handsome face that could pass for a young man
那一刻 俊俏如青年的妃子脸庞
looked like a loving mother's face.
露出了慈母一般的神情
These are the names of Fengming's family and those connected to her.
这是风明亲族与相关人士的名簿
I heard that she was kidnapped and sold off, but…
虽然说是被绑架然后卖掉的 但是…
PREVIEW OF NEXT EPISODE
（下集预告）
Next Episode, "The Eunuch and the Courtesan."
下一集 《宦官与娼妓》
Subtitle translation by: Yukimi Ohashi
字幕翻译：欧德慧